RUBÉN PÉREZ-SANZ

UAB and BSE

☑ rubenprzsnz@gmail.comWebpage: Rubén Pérez-Sanz

RESEARCH

Job Market Paper: Firm Heterogeneity and Collective Agreements: a Structural Model of Minimum Wages in Spain

Does widespread coverage of collective agreements introduce inefficiencies in the labour market? How are firms of different sizes affected? Participants in collective agreements set the minimum wage that fits them best, not internalising the effects imposed on non-participants. I analyse minimum wage bargaining and its effects on workers and firms in a model of two-sided heterogeneity with on-the-job search. I estimate the model using Spanish Social Security records for the metal industry in Madrid. By exogenously varying minimum wage levels, I show that large firms gain most from raising minimum wages. This is through two channels. On the one hand, large firms increase their advantage in hiring over small firms. On the other hand, higher minimum wages slow down wage growth. This especially decreases the wage bill for large firms because they hire more experienced workers. Lastly, I find that letting everyone participate in collective bargaining would result in a lower wage floor of $\in 1150$ instead of $\in 1250$. The profits of large firms would be reduced by 4.4% and those of small firms increased by 6.9%.

Working papers

• Union Coordination under the Presence of Externalities and Costs in an Oligopoly Market

EDUCATION

Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona PhD in Economics Thesis Advisor: Joan Llull	2018 - Present
Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona M.Res. in Economics	2016 - 2018
Universidad Carlos III de Madrid M.Sc. in Economics	2015 - 2016
CIFF M.Sc. in Statistics	2008 - 2009
Universidad Autonoma de Madrid Bachelor in Economics	2002 - 2008
PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE	
The Econometrics Journal Replication team	2021 - Present
MOVE Fundation Research Assistant of Joan Llull and Robert Miller	2020 - Present
The Economic Journal Replication team	2019 - Present

Banco Sabadell Research Assistant (Intership)	2019
Santander Bank UK London: Process Design and Change Management Consultant	2014 - 2015
Banco Santander Process Design and Change Management Consultant	2011 - 2014
Santander Bank Research Assistant (Internship)	2010
IBERIA L.A.E. Price Analyst	2009
Dinners Club Analyst	2009
HONOURS AND AWARDS	
PIF-UAB Predoctoral Fellowship	2018-2022
Barcelona GSE - UAB IDEA Ph.D. Track Fellowship Agreement	2017-2018
TEACHING	
Econometrics I (undergraduate), UAB Instructor	2021 Fall
Econometrics I (graduate), UAB Teaching assistant of Pau Milan	2021 $Winter$
Math Brush-up (graduate), UAB Instructor	2020 Fall
Structural Microeconometrics (graduate), UAB Teaching assistant of Joan Llull	2020 $Winter$
Statistics II (undergraduate), UAB Teaching assistant of Vladimir Zaiats	$2021 \ Spring$
Math Brush-up (graduate), UAB Instructor	2019 Fall
SEMINARS AND PRESENTATIONS	
SSSI, Moscow, Online	June 2021
Bellaterra Applied Working Group, Online	June 2021
Essex-Barcelona Workshop on Labor Economics, Online	May 2021
Bellaterra Applied Working Group, Online	March 2020
Bellaterra Applied Working Group, Barcelona	May 2019
EVENT ORGANIZATION	
Coorganizer: BSE PhD Jamboree	2019
EVENT ORGANIZATION	

SKILLS

Programming skills:

Stata, MATLAB, GAUS, LATEX, Eviews, Mathematica, MAPLE, R

Languages:

Spanish (Native) English (Advance) Catalan (Basic), German (Basic).

REFERENCES

Joan Llull

Associate Professor of Economics MOVE, UAB and BSE joan.llull@movebarcelona.eu

Javier Fernandez-Blanco

Associate Professor of Economics UAB, MOVE and BSE javier.fernandez@barcelonagse.eu

Hanna Wang

Assistant Professor MOVE, UAB and BSE hannaw.econ@gmail.com